Welcome back to AM Northwest. When it's
time to clean out your parents' home,
knowing where to begin
can feel overwhelming.
But our next guest can help you get started.
We welcome back antique appraiser Gary Germer.
Good morning, Gary.
Hi, Helen. How are you doing?
Good. So when it comes to working on your
family's estate, which is basically the house and
everything in it,
one of the most important things you say is
make sure that you take care of things ahead of
time.
So pre-plan where things are going to go.
That's true. I think that, you know,
half of what I do is liquidate things.
The other half is work
as family counselor.
And so it makes it so much easier if it's clear
what, you know, each person in the family is
supposed to get.
So there's no fighting afterwards.
And it needs to be in writing.
If you have an executor, they
have to follow what's in writing.
So masking tape on the bottom of a
piece of furniture doesn't count.
Yeah, that's right.
Right. So make sure it's in writing and then
make sure that everyone knows where the account
numbers are
or the hidden money is or the jewelry
is, that kind of stuff, right?
Yeah, I think, my guess is there's millions of
dollars in money and jewelry thrown in landfills
because people were clearing out an estate
and didn't know that mom had left anything.
Right.
I had a friend who had a house. They
were cleaning out their uncle's house.
And they tried to give the sofa
away. It was a beat up, dirty sofa.
And no one would take it.
And in the end, they threw it away.
They threw it in a dumpster and a hundred dollar,
packed a hundred dollar bill show up and hit
him in the head.
And they found $67,000 in the sofa.
Wow.
Yeah, they're kind of wondering what was
in the matching chair that they gave away.
But they, you know, so
this happens regularly.
So this is where you don't have to tell everyone,
but put it with your papers or tell your best
friend somewhere.
Hey, you know, this is
where I keep my stuff.
And I'm sure you, well, you need to have
an executor, one person to be the executor.
One person.
And the only thing you can do is have
two executors that are even, you know,
equal, equal.
Right.
So one person makes the decision.
And it's a court state fact.
Yeah.
All right.
You say dealing after
the fact with an estate.
So first of all, sell
first, donate second.
Yep.
Everybody gets excited.
If you're going to be downsizing or if
someone's past, you're dealing with an estate,
they get excited and they
find the most valuable things.
And want to give.
And then they just get kind of frantic
and overwhelmed by how much is there.
And so my feeling is, is that the more you can
sell at the sale or even give away at the sale,
like clothing, for example, you
don't have to haul it away then.
You can just get it on Sunday
afternoon at one o'clock, set it free.
It's all free.
Whoever wants the clothing can have it.
Things like that.
So if you can, the less you have to do
beforehand, as far as giving things away,
you're better off.
Because you have a chance of selling it.
You don't have to move it.
You say as you're clearing out the house,
definitely throw out the wet garbage,
old food, old newspapers.
Old newspapers aren't really
worth anything anymore.
Not really.
I mean, you have all
the big dates, Mount St.
Helens blowing, you know, the Challenger
explosion and all these big events.
Everybody saves those newspapers.
So there's hundreds and
thousands of them around.
They're not really worth a lot.
Go ahead and recycle them.
Go recycle the magazines by and large.
You can do that and get rid of that.
That's obvious.
Give away what's been
willed, what's been promised.
And then you're down to
what you have to deal with.
And it depends on if you're going
to hire a service or do it yourself.
You want to take your time
and go through things.
Find the hidden money.
Books, as everybody knows, you've got to shake
out the books because that's a classic place
for hiding money.
Well, and as you mentioned earlier, too,
looking in sofas, looking in pockets,
looking in purses, that kind
of stuff, it's important to do.
Yeah, exactly.
And shoeboxes.
One of the most favorite places.
People have is button jars to put jewelry in
because it disappears in a jar of buttons.
And another one is behind doors, meaning step
into the closet, turn around and look up above
the door on the inside of the closet.
That's a favorite place.
Oh, wow.
I had no idea.
OK, so after you've sold or you're about ready
to sell and donate, you say get things sorted
by subject.
Yeah, it's somewhat of the
Marie Kondo effect here.
You know that way you can kind of.
You know, you can sort of go through
that a way of approaching it.
And then by subject, you know
what you need to learn about.
So, you know, the clothes
go through all the clothes.
And if there's, you know, if you've had if they
have designer clothes, really great vintage
clothes, stuff like that, you know, to market
those differently than the working clothes that
might be a meet up.
The books and you can
get them all together.
You sort and go through it
are the most valuable books.
Is there anything you need
to do with certain things?
Like, do you need to make
sure everything's polished?
Do you need to make
sure everything's done?
Do you need to make sure everything's polished
and clean and that kind of stuff when you're
getting ready to have, say, an
estate sale if you decide to do one?
Yeah, I'm a big believer in that.
My belief, and I've been in this a lot
of years, that if you don't clean it,
make it look nice, why is the person
going to buy it want to have it?
Right.
People, when they would come and bring stuff
to me, they want me to buy the best from things
that were not polished and were
dirty because they didn't care.
So you could get it at a better price.
So the more you make it look appealing is the
reason Nordstrom sets up their stores the way
they do is to really make sure that you're
not buying things that are not polished.
So they want to draw you and make it
appealing, make it easy to get around,
make it easy to see things and
make it impulsive to buy it.
You talk about hiring a professional.
How do you know when you need a professional
and what kind of professional do you need?
Well, if you're going to do the sale yourself,
90% of an estate sale, more of it is just labor.
It's just working, cleaning,
polishing, setting up.
But the 10% is pricing and
that's where people get stuck.
So a lot of appraisers like myself or other
estate sale people, you can hire them.
They'll buy the hour per day to come price your
sale and help you do it and their expertise.
So then you don't have to worry that maybe
what you thought was valuable really isn't.
And yet these things you didn't know
were valuable might be very valuable.
So you want to follow up on those.
If you want to hire a professional to run the
whole thing, then what you need to do is simply
do what we said.
Get rid of the wet garbage
and everything bad.
Give all the things you're going to take or
give away, give away things you're keeping,
you keep and then let them handle it.
And they should be able to do it.
From soup to nuts, meaning they set it up,
run the sale, clean the house out at the end.
So you're ended up with an empty house.
And you want to hire them when
you're feeling overwhelmed.
Closing a house is a very emotional thing.
No kidding.
And so if you're feeling overwhelmed by it,
it's worth it to hire somebody to do it for you.
If you have collections, if dad collected big
collections like art or tools or toys or whatever
it is he might have collected,
you want to get a person in.
Who is specialized in that
and who can guide you.
And if you're hiring an appraiser to
help you do this and help you sort it,
never, never, never, never
sell to the appraiser.
It's just a, yeah, because
it can be a license to steal.
They'll have people who come in and claim to
be this appraiser and then they are setting the
price.
So you're asking them to
buy it and set the price.
It's an opportunity to
really lose some money.
Hire them, pay them by the hour, pay them
a fee to help you sort and price things.
That sounds good.
Gary, all good information.
I want to tell folks if they'd like to find
out more, just go to our website at KATU.com.